Register to The David Kraehenbuehl Papers
Yale University Music Library
The David Kraehenbuehl Papers
1913-2000
MSS 79
Yale University Music Library
10
(18 boxes)
Music, correspondence and other papers, photographs, and additional materials by and about the American composer, music theorist, and educator David Kraehenbuehl (1923-1997)
Kraehenbuehl, David
Conditions Governing Access
The Papers are open to researchers by appointment. There are no restricted materials in the collection. Please contact the Special Collections staff to schedule an appointment.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The David Kraehenbuehl Papers were established in the Music Library of Yale University by Marie Kraehenbuehl in August 1999.
Arrangement
In 10 series as follows: I. Music. II. Writings. III. Correspondence. IV. Programs and Publicity. V. Clippings and Scrapbooks. VI. Photographs. VII. Biographical Material. VIII. Miscellaneous Materials. IX. Sound Recordings. X. Additions.
Scope and Contents
The David Kraehenbuehl Papers consists of ten linear feet of archival material, divided into ten series. Series I, Music, comprises the bulk of the papers and contains Kraehenbuehl's musical compositions for all genres in manuscript, mechanical reproduction, and published versions. Series II contains a large number of writings by Kraehenbuehl, as well as writings by others that were important to Kraehenbuehl or used as texts in his musical compositions. Correspondence appears in Series III, while Series IV holds programs and publicity materials that feature music by Kraehenbuehl. Newspaper clippings and scrapbooks comprise Series V. In this series, clippings were photocopied onto acid-free paper to preserve them, and the originals discarded. The three scrapbooks were microfilmed to preserve their contents. Original documents found in the scrapbooks, such as photographs and correspondence, were subsequently removed and reassigned to their corresponding series in the papers. The original scrapbooks were then discarded. Photographs appear in Series VI, with each photograph assigned a unique number. Biographical and miscellaneous materials comprise Series VII and Series VIII respectively. All sound recordings, Series IX, have been transferred to the Historical Sound Recordings Collection, a separate department within the Music Library. Preservation transfers were made of all archival recordings onto reel-to-reel tape, and listening copies were prepared on compact discs. Finally, Series X accommodates additions to the papers that were received after the completion of this finding aid. Because the contents of Series X will change as new material is acquired, the most current inventory of additions to the Kraehenbuehl Papers will be kept on file in the Music Library Office.
Biographical / Historical
The son of John O. and Kathryn A. Kraehenbuehl, David Kraehenbuehl was born in Urbana, Illinois, on September 15, 1923. His father was a professor of electrical engineering at the University of Illinois, and his mother taught the boy his first piano lessons at the age of 5. He attended private and experimental schools in Urbana, including the University of Illinois High School, from which he graduated in 1939. That same year, at the age of 16, Kraehenbuehl entered the University of Illinois. During his years at Illinois, Kraehenbuehl studied piano with Stanley Fletcher, and he wrote his first significant musical compositions. He was elected to three honor societies, Phi Beta Kappa, Phi Kappa Phi, and Phi Kappa Lambda, became a Lieutenant Colonel in the ROTC in command of the University of Illinois student Signal Corp unit, and demonstrated sufficient promise as a composer, pianist, and flautist to receive the Kate Neal Kinley Fellowship in the Arts. At his college graduation in 1943, Kraehenbuehl was awarded degrees in music (Bachelor of Music) and German and mathematics (Bachelor of Arts). Kraehenbuehl entered the Army following graduation and saw duty in the Philippines and Japan. He attained the rank of captain by the time of his discharge in 1946.
Following his return to Urbana, Kraehenbuehl took a competitive examination given to prospective students of Paul Hindemith. He won the one remaining place in Hindemith's class. In August, 1947, Kraehenbuehl married Marie Marek, a cello student at the University of Illinois, and the following month the young couple moved to New Haven, where Kraehenbuehl began his studies in the Yale School of Music. David and Marie wrote frequent reports of their activities and sent them back to family members in Illinois. Their letters, collected in the family correspondence in Series III of these papers, provide a fascinating look at life in the Yale School of Music, as well as musical activities in New Haven, during the years 1947 to 1949. David Kraehenbuehl received the Bachelor of Music degree from Yale in 1948, and in 1949 he received the Master of Music degree in musical composition. With a strong recommendation from Hindemith, Kraehenbuehl also received the Ditson Fellowship for Foreign Study. During the academic year 1949-1950 the Kraehenbuehls lived in Basel, Switzerland, where David attended classes given at the Schola Cantorum Basiliensis by Ina Lohr, Joseph Bopp, and Edward Mueller. He also performed under the directorship of Paul Sacher in the Basel Kammerchor and the Basel Kammerorchester.
Upon his return from Switzerland, Kraehenbuehl was appointed Assistant Professor of music history and theory at Colorado College in Colorado Springs, a position he held until 1953. In addition to his teaching duties, Kraehenbuehl remained active as a performer and conductor. He founded the Colorado College Collegium Musicum, a group modeled on Hindemith's Collegium Musicum at Yale that performed medieval, renaissance, Baroque, and occasionally contemporary music. Kraehenbuehl also pursued activities as a journalist and served as music editor, critic, and essayist for the Colorado Springs Free Press.
In 1953, when Hindemith returned permanently to Europe, Kraehenbuehl joined the faculty of the Yale School of Music and assumed Hindemith's teaching duties. In New Haven, he continued to pursue a wide range of musical activities. These included serving as Musical Director of the New Haven Chorale, performing with and guest conducting the New Haven Symphony Orchestra, and serving as curator of the Yale Collection of Musical Instruments. In 1957 Kraehenbuehl made a seminal contribution to the field of music theory in the United States by serving as the founding editor of the Journal of Music Theory. The following year Kraehenbuehl, in collaboration with Edgar Coons, published the article "Information as a Measure of Structure in Music." (Journal of Music Theory, vol. 2, pp. 127-161) This ground breaking article applied nascent information and probability theories to music. During his tenures in Colorado Springs and New Haven, however, musical composition remained foremost among Kraehenbuehl's many activities. He created works for several combinations of instruments and/or voices throughout the 1950s, works that were premiered by the best musicians in Colorado and Connecticut.
Kraehenbuehl's career took an unexpected turn in 1960, one year after receiving tenure at Yale. In that year he resigned his faculty post and moved to Princeton, New Jersey, to found the New School for Music Study, along with the noted piano pedagogues Frances Clark and Louise Goss. Apart from one school year teaching music theory at Westminster Choir College, 1967-1968, Kraehenbuehl never held another academic appointment. Instead, he devoted himself to the training of piano teachers, and in doing so he helped to raise the level of piano study in the United States. He composed and arranged a number of pieces for beginning and intermediate piano students, many of which became staples in the teaching repertory of American piano teachers. In 1967 he left the New School and, with Richard Chronister and Thomas McBeth, founded the National Keyboard Arts Association. In this new organization, Kraehenbuehl wrote extensively on the topic of piano pedagogy, published numerous articles in NKAA's periodical Keyboard Arts, and traveled across the country to give master classes, performances, and lectures.
A convert to Roman Catholicism, Kraehenbuehl also took up the musical challenges presented by the dictates of the Second Vatican Council (1962-65). In 1967 his Mass for the People of God won first prize in a competition sponsored by the J. S. Paluch Company of Chicago, a firm that specialized in publishing Roman Catholic church music. In 1968 Kraehenbuehl was appointed music editor, and later managing editor, for the Paluch Company. In that role he composed and commissioned service music that is still used today in Catholic churches across the United States. In 1982 David and Marie moved to Trempealeau, Wisconsin, where David continued to compose and perform. David Kraehenbuehl died in La Crosse, Wisconsin, on January 3, 1997. Following Kraehenbuehl's death, his friend Charles Burkhart published a warm and informative tribute, "Remembering David Kraehenbuehl," in the Journal of Music Theory. (vol. 41, pp. 183-192) Readers desiring more information about Kraehenbuehl's life and work are directed to Burkhart's article, found in these papers in Box 8, Folder 137, and to the several versions of Kraehenbuehl's curriculum vitae, updated by Marie and found in Box 13, Folder 200.
Braden, Martha; Burkhart, Charles (Charles L.); Cohen, Sol B., 1891-1988; Fletcher, Stanley, 1910-1988; Frye, Christopher B., 1956-; Heiden, Bernhard, 1910-2000; Hillis, Margaret, 1921-1998; Hindemith, Gertrud, 1900-1967; Hindemith, Paul, 1895-1963; Kort, Ellen, 1936-; Kraehenbuehl, David; Kraehenbuehl, Marie; Lanner, Max; Leonhardt, Gustav, 1928-2012; Light, Christopher U.; Lohr, Ina; Martirano, Dorothy; Müller, Hannelore; Sacher, Paul, 1906-1999; Slade, Frances F.; Watkins, Armin; Winternitz, Emanuel, 1898-; J.S. Paluch Company; National Keyboard Arts Associates; New School for Music Study; Yale School of Music
- Music, Series I
  - Music by David Kraehenbuehl
    - Stage Works, I.A
      - City scene.
        General
        see entries for Choral Music.
      - The fisherman and his soul: a ballet in two acts for narrator and chamber orchestra / by David Kraehenbuehl., 1 manuscript score (115 + 134 p.); 32 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
        Holograph in pencil and ink, annotations in pencil, colored pencil, ink, and crayon.
        For narrator, oboe/English horn, clarinet, trumpet, horn, violin I, violin II, viola, violoncello, double bass, and piano.
        Text cues written in.
        At end: Colorado Springs, 16 Feb. 1953.
      - The fisherman and his soul / David Kraehenbuehl., 10 manuscript parts (144 p. total); 32 cm. (Box 1, Folder 2)
        Holograph in ink, annotations in pencil, colored pencil, and taped in. Some passages are copyist's manuscript.
        Parts for: oboe/English horn, clarinet, trumpet, horn, violin I, violin II, viola, violoncello, double bass, piano.
      - [Fisherman and his soul; arr.], 1 manuscript score (39 + 43 p.); 32 cm. (Box 1, Folder 3)
        Holograph in ink, annotations in pencil, colored pencil, and taped in.
        Arr. for piano, 4-hands.
        Text cues written in score and taped in.
        Incomplete: lacks all but Act I, Scene III, and Act II, Scenes I-III.
      - [Traum eines Harlekins. Vocal score] Ein Traum eines Harlekins: Oper in einem Akt / libretto by François Christophe; music by David Kraehenbuehl., 1 manuscript vocal score (11 p.); 31 cm. (Box 1, Folder 4)
        Holograph in pencil.
        Text in German.
    - Orchestral and Band Works, I.B
      - [Archaic images] Seven archaic images: variations for full orchestra based on poems of Thomas Merton / by David Kraehenbuehl. -- c.1974 by David Kraehenbuehl., 1 manuscript score (26 p.) + 31 manuscript parts (41 p. total); 38 and 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 5)
        Holograph in ink, cut-outs.
        Theme. -- Variation I. "A procession..." -- Variation II. "The magic door wide open..." -- Variation III. "The cauldron seething..." -- Variation IV. "Night council..." -- Variation V. "Winter morning...drums, banners and snow." -- Variation VI. "Why do we dance...?" -- Variation VII. "The sadness of laws..."
        On title page: Written for the Symphony School of America.
        At end: Cranbury, New Jersey, March 20, 1974.
      - [Archaic images; arr.] Seven archaic images: variations for 2 pianos, 8 hands, based on poems by Thomas Merton / by David Kraehenbuehl., 1 manuscript score (51 p.); 28 cm. (Box 1, Folder 6)
        At end: Cranbury, N.J., March 10, 1974.
      - [Archaic images; arr.] Seven archaic images: variations for 2 pianos, 8 hands, based on poems by Thomas Merton / by David Kraehenbuehl., 1 manuscript score (51 p.); 28 cm. (Box 1, Folder 6)
        Photocopy of holograph, annotations in pencil.
        Instrumental cues.
      - [Celebrations; arr.] Celebrations: a modern concerto for piano and orchestra or band / David Kraehenbuehl., 1 manuscript score (29 p.); 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 7)
        Accompaniment arr. for 2nd piano.
        On title page: Dedicated to youthful performers and youthful listeners.
        At end: Princeton, N.J., February 1961.
      - Changes: etude no. 2 for orchestra / by David Kraehenbuehl -- c.1978 by David Kraehenbuehl., 1 manuscript score (21 p.) + 28 manuscript parts (38 p. total); 38 and 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 8)
        Holograph in ink.
        On title page: Written for Frank Italiano and the Symphony School of America.
        "Although this work may be a challenge for the individual players and the various sections of the orchestra, its basic purpose is to test the skills of the orchestral conductor."
        At end: Duration: 6' 05", Cranbury, N.J., March 19, 1978.
        In envelope (discarded) marked: Sym. School of America, Conductor's Competition, Hugo Huss won 1st, became La Crosse Sym. Conductor consequently.
      - Changes: etude no. 2 for orchestra / by David Kraehenbuehl -- c.1978 by David Kraehenbuehl., 1 manuscript score (21 p.); 39 cm. (Box 1, Folder 8)
        Photocopy of holograph.
        In same envelope as above.
      - [Changes. Sketches] Changes., 1 manuscript score (22 p.); 34 cm. (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - A concert of the humours: for chamber orchestra / by David Kraehenbuehl. -- 1962., 1 manuscript score (28 p.) + 17 manuscript parts (41 p. total); 38 and 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 10)
        I. Melancholic. -- II. Choleric. -- III. Phlegmatic. -- IV. Sanguine.
        P.2 of violin II part is a later recopy.
        On title page: Written for the Kinhaven Camp Orchestra.
        At end: May 6, 1962, Princeton, N.J.
      - A concert of the humours: for chamber orchestra / by David Kraehenbuehl., 1 manuscript score (28 p.); 39 cm. (Box 1, Folder 11)
        "Score in C."
        On title page: Written for the Kinhaven Camp Orchestra, 1962.
      - A concert of the humours / David Kraehenbuehl., 17 manuscript parts (40 p. total); 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 11)
        Multiple copies of some parts.
      - A concert of the mysteries / by David Kraehenbuehl -- 1960., 1 manuscript score (20 p.) + 15 manuscript parts (25 p. total); 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 12)
        Holograph in ink, corrections taped in and cut out.
        For 9 violins, 3 violas, 2 violoncello, and 1 double bass.
        On title page: Composed for the Amerita Strings.
        At end: Princeton, N.J., Feast of the Holy Rosary, 1960.
      - A concert of the mysteries (sketches), 20 manuscript p. of music; 32 cm. (Box 1, Folder 12)
        Holograph in pencil, annotations in colored pencil.
        Some pages unidentified, possibly sketches for other works.
      - A concert of the mysteries (II): meditations for two pianists at one piano and orchestra / by David Kraehenbuehl. -- 1975., 1 manuscript score (64 p.) + 27 manuscript parts (51 p. total); 39 + 35 cm. (Box 2, Folder 13)
        Holograph in ink, cut-outs in some parts.
        I. The Annunciation. -- II. The Visitation. -- III. The Nativity. -- IV. The Presentation. -- V. The Finding in the Temple. -- VI. The Agony in the Garden. -- VII. The Scourging. -- VIII. The Crowning with Thorns. -- IX. The Carrying of the Cross. -- X. The Crucifixion. -- XI. The Resurrection. -- XII. The Ascension. -- XIII. The Descent of the Holy Spirit. -- XIV. The Assumption of Mary. -- XV. The Coronation of Mary.
        On title page: Written for Nancy Arganbright and Dallas Weekley and the Symphony School of America, Frank Italiano, director.
        At end: 20' 10", Cranbury, New Jersey, Good Shepherd Sunday, April 20, 1975.
      - [Concert of the mysteries, II; arr.] A concert of the mysteries (II): meditations for two pianists at one piano and orchestra / by David Kraehenbuehl -- c.1975 by David Kraehenbuehl., 1 manuscript score (54 p.); 38 cm. (Box 2, Folder 14)
        Arr. for 2 pianos, 8 hands.
        On title page: Written for Nancy Arganbright, Dallas Weekley, and the American Symphony School, Frank Italiano, director.
        At end: 20' 10", Cranbury, New Jersey, Feast of the Presentation, February 2, 1975.
      - [Concert of the mysteries, II; arr.] A concert of the mysteries (II): meditations for two pianists at one piano and orchestra / by David Kraehenbuehl -- c.1975 by David Kraehenbuehl., 1 manuscript score (54 p.); 39 cm. (Box 2, Folder 15)
        Photocopy of holograph, annotations in pencil, cuts pasted in.
        3 copies.
      - Concerto da chiesa: for string orchestra / by David Kraehenbuehl. -- c.1994 by David Kraehenbuehl., 1 score (22 p.); 28 cm. (Box 2, Folder 16)
        Computer-generated score.
        I. Aria. -- II. Fugue. -- III. Ground. -- IV. Rondeau.
        Program note and biographical note printed on score.
        Arrangement of the Sonata da chiesa for oboe, harpsichord, and violoncello.
        On title page: 1949.
      - [Diptych, band] Diptych for concert band / David Kraehenbuehl., 1 manuscript score (61 p.); 44 cm. (Box 16, Folder 224)
        Holograph in ink, with erasures and corrections.
        At end: For the Yale University Band and Keith Wilson, Colorado Springs, 2 August 1951.
      - [Diptych, piano, chamber orchestra] Diptych: for piano and chamber orchestra / David Kraehenbuehl -- 1966., 1 manuscript score (64 p.) + 18 manuscript parts (58 p. total); 38 and 35 cm. (Box 2, Folder 17)
        Holograph in ink, portions of parts cut out.
        I. Celebrations. II. Retrospects.
        At end: Princeton, N.J., June 5, 1966.
      - [Diptych, piano, chamber orchestra; arr.] Diptych: for piano and chamber orchestra / David Kraehenbuehl -- 1966., 1 manuscript score (50 [i.e. 51] p.); 35 cm. (Box 2, Folder 18)
        Holograph in ink, portions of score cut out.
        Accompaniment arr. for piano.
        Includes additional p. 46 [piano cadenza, not in full score]
        At end: Princeton, N.J., March 23, 1976.
      - Ephemera metamorphose: a suite for orchestra / by [David Kraehenbuehl] -- 1986., 1 manuscript score (48 p.); 44 cm. (Box 16, Folder 225)
        1. Overture. -- 2. Waltz. -- 3. March. -- 4. Tango. -- 5. Jam. -- 6. Perpetual Motion.
        "A variation on Opus 19 of Arnold Schönberg."
        At end: September 16, 1986.
      - [Ephemera metamorphose. Sketches] Ephemera metamorphose: C score., 1 manuscript score (60 p.); 31 cm. (Box 2, Folder 19)
        I. Prelude. -- II. Waltz. -- III. March. -- IV. Tango. -- V. Blues [erased] -- VI. Perpetual Motion.
        At end: Total time: 10' 15"
      - Epitaphs concertant: a concerto for piano and orchestra / David Kraehenbuehl., 1 manuscript score (72 p.); 44 cm. (Box 16, Folder 226)
        I. For a magician. -- II. For a stranger -- For a madman. -- III. For a hero -- For a coward. -- IV. For a leader of men.
        At end: For Armin Watkins, August 25, 1955, New Haven, Conn.
      - [Etudes, orchestra, no. 1] Etude for orchestra / by David Kraehenbuehl. -- c.1977 by David Kraehenbuehl., 1 manuscript score (24 p.) + 19 parts (24 p. total); 39 and 35 cm. (Box 2, Folder 20)
        Holograph in ink, photocopy of holograph, cut-outs.
        "The purpose of this work is not to test the skills of individual players or even sections of the orchestra, but rather to rehearse those skills that are essential to polished performance by a large group of instrumentalists and their conductor..."
        At end: 5' 00", Cranbury, New Jersey, April 21, 1977.
      - [Etudes, orchestra, no. 2]
        see: Changes: etude no. 2 for orchestra
      - Homáge á Shostakovich [sic]
        see: [Russian trilogy. Homáge á Shostakovich]
      - Kaleidoscope: an orchestral suite for young people / by David Kraehenbuehl., 1 manuscript score (27 [i.e. 24] p.) + 18 parts; 43 and 23 cm. (Box 16, Folder 227)
        pp. 12-14 = pp. 22-24
        I. Turn slow. -- II. Turn fast. -- III. Turn on and on.
        "Composed for Frank Brieff and the New Haven Symphony."
        At end: New Haven, Conn., November 8, 1958.
      - La Crosse sketches / by David Kraehenbuehl., 1 manuscript score (78 [i.e. 80] p.) + 24 manuscript parts (109 p. total); 36 and 28 cm. (Box 2, Folder 21)
        Photocopy of holograph, annotations in colored pencil.
        For orchestra.
        I. On the River. -- II. Downtown: Six Miniatures.
        On title page: Commissioned by the La Crosse Symphony Orchestra in celebration of its 90th season, 1988-1989.
        At end: total 10' 15"
        In envelope (discarded) marked: January 1988.
      - [La Crosse sketches. (Sketches)] La Crosse sketches., 1 manuscript score (3 p.); 31 cm. (Box 2, Folder 22)
        I. Dawn to Dusk. -- II. Three Rivers. -- III. Celebrations.
        In envelope above.
      - Partita d'Apollone: for solo harp and chamber orchestra / by David Kraehenbuehl. -- c.1979 by David Kraehenbuehl., 1 manuscript score (22 p.) + 15 manuscript parts; 39 and 28 cm. (Box 2, Folder 23)
        Preludio. -- Allemanda. -- Corrente. -- Sarabanda. -- Gavotta. -- Giga.
        At end: December 17, 1978, Cranbury, New Jersey.
      - Partita d'Apollone: for solo harp and chamber orchestra / by David Kraehenbuehl. -- c.1979 by David Kraehenbuehl., 1 manuscript score (22 p.); 42 cm. (Box 16, Folder 228)
      - [Partita d'Apollone. Harp part] Partita d'Apollone / David Kraehenbuehl., 1 manuscript part (11 p.); 35 cm. (Box 2, Folder 23)
      - [Partita d'Apollone; arr.] Apollonian suite: for solo harp and chamber orchestra / David Kraehenbuehl., 1 manuscript score (18 p.); 30 cm. (Box 2, Folder 24)
        Accompaniment reduced to 2-3 staves with instrumental cues.
        Prelude. -- Allemande. -- Corrente. -- Sarabande. -- Gavotte. -- Gigue.
        At end: Cranbury, N.J., December 17, 1978.
      - Ritual / David Kraehenbuehl., 1 manuscript score (22 p.) + 31 manuscript parts (47 p. total); 44 and 28 cm. (Box 16, Folder 229)
        For band.
        At end: 6 Sep 55
      - Ritual / David Kraehenbuehl., 1 manuscript score (22 p.) + 31 manuscript parts (47 p. total); 45 and 28 cm. (Box 16, Folder 230)
        Photocopy of holograph, pencil corrections to bassoon parts.
        Holograph title page.
        Multiple copies of parts. Includes recopy of baritone part in treble clef.
      - [Russian trilogy. Homáge á Shostakovich [sic]] A Russian trilogy: Homáge á Shostakovich [sic] / David Kraehenbuehl. -- c1996 by David Kraehenbuehl., 1 score (44 p.); 28 cm. (Box 2, Folder 25)
        Computer-generated score, annotations in pencil.
      - Seven archaic images
        see: Archaic images
      - Toccata sinfonica / David Kraehenbuehl. -- c.1983 by Symphony School of America., 1 manuscript score (26 p.); 28 cm. (Box 3, Folder 26)
        Photocopy of holograph, annotations in colored ink.
        At end: 7' 45", La Crosse, Wisconsin, May 8, 1983.